not even the stunning beauty of Alaska's
Prince William sound can hide the deep
and Lasting scar just beneath the
surface there are some folks that I
cannot get to talk to anybody about the
spill because it brings back nightmares
The Spill began at 12:04 a.m. on March
24th 1989 when the Exon vald ran a
ground on blly
reath fre get oil and we're going to be
here for a while over the the course of
56 days the black cloud spread damaging
1300 M of
Shoreline 10,000 people helped clean it
up it took more than four Summers and
cost Exxon $2 billion patience Falkner
lives in Cordova Alaska the largest
fishing town on the sound 21 years later
things look pretty normal well it does
look nice and normal we don't have any
Herring and that's why Mark King's boat
is parked in a warehouse the former
Herring fisherman used to pull in up to
$150,000 per year now he makes about
50,000 fishing salmon Herring basically
disappeared within 3 years of the spill
your Hope was to pass this business on
to your kids oh definitely but now your
kids are all gone yeah they're gone they
they aren't involved in the fishing
business they didn't have the
opportunity that I had growing up here
while Herring populations are still
devastated other species such as salmon
and bald eagles have recovered but
perhaps what's most remarkable is what
never went away and you can find in just
a short plane ride from Cordova here
along the shoreline all you need to do
is move a couple of rocks and you can
strike oil Exxon vald oil 21 years later
in fact more than 21,000 gallons of oil
are still left from The Spill naturally
decreasing at a rate of 0 to 4% per year
it could take decades or even centuries
before it's all gone it still smells and
researcher David Jenka says two decades
later the oil is still a threat there
are salmon streams nearby there are
birds uh that that utilize these beaches
along with the oil a bitterness remains
a jury awarded fisherman and other
residents along the sound $5 billion but
Exxon appealed and only had to pay 57
million while the community has paid a
heavy price we've had tons of divorces
tons of domestic violence alcohol abuse
and suicides so prevention is now the
focus from the area you can see barges
stationed on the water with equipment to
handle a spill and oil spill drills like
this one are held regularly if there was
another oil spill here like the one that
we had it would be devastating um and
and there is that constant fear um
around the people that live here as for
the infamous tanker by law it can never
enter these Alaskan Waters ever again
Ben Tracy CBS News Cordova
Alaska